Okay, בוקר טוב boker tov everybody.
Today's בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is י"ד, yud-dalet, 27th
day of עומר, Omer, 27th day of March, what are we going
to do when it gets to April? I don't know, okay.
Anyway, and we pick up at the bottom of י"ג עמוד ב'
yud-gimmel amud-bet and לימא כתנאי leima k'tana-ei and the גמרא Gemara is
in the middle of a great of a good debate. It is
so nice, I just got to say this for the record, a
little breath of fresh air that we are out of all the
דרשות drashot of the פסוקים psukim and we're actually talking about some
conceptual questions and so on. So we're dealing with the question about
like what are the four עבודה, avodah, right, well we know the
four עבודה: avodah: שחיטה shechita the slaughtering, קבלת הדם kabbalas hadam catching
the blood, הולכה holacha bringing it to the altar and זריקה zerika
throwing it on the altar. A thought during any one of those
עבודות avodot for about שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, you know, to the
to that to doing it for not the sake of the sacrifice
can have an effect. If it's a normal sacrifice it'll mean it
doesn't עולה לבעלים olei l'baalim and if it's the חטאת chatas or
the פסח pesach it means that it's invalid. Similarly that's the time
to be having like you know thoughts about פיגול pigul and whatever
that also got discussed, we're now having a very, פיגול's pigul going
to be a regular part of our discussion. The question in the
גמרא Gemara is: what is the story with dipping the finger into
the blood of the חטאת? chatas? Is that a type of a
הולכה? holacha? Okay, this is by the inner חטאות, chata'ot, now actually
the outer חטאות chata'ot as well, the כהן Kohen would dip his
finger in and put them at the corner of the outer altar.
The only difference is and the גמרא's Gemara going to get to
this in a minute, that the פסוק pasuk doesn't explicitly say וטבל
את אצבעו בדם, v'taval et etzba'o badam, dip your finger in the
blood. It makes it clear that you are, it speaks about, we'll
get to that in a minute, but it doesn't explicitly describe that
act. By the inner חטאת chatas where you put it on the
inner altar like we say on יום כיפור Yom Kippur whatever, that's
just one example of an inner חטאת, chatas,
then it explicitly says dip your finger in the blood. And therefore
the question is, since it is an עבודה avodah that is necessary,
it has to be done, there's no way not to do it,
so it's a necessary part of the כפרה kapara process and not
only that, the תורה Torah is explicitly mentioning it, it should have
the status of a one of the עבודות. avodot. Which עבודה? avodah?
It should be like הולכה, holacha, this is the what the גמרא
Gemara says in passing, because it's part of getting the blood to
the altar, it's not the actual placing on the altar, but a
necessary process to get it, not just to physically transport it, but
it actually has to be gotten through the dipping of the finger
and so on, so it's part of that getting it to the
altar, it should be הולכה, holacha, that is one position.
I would have thought like זריקה zerika because you're putting blood...
I know, that's why I mentioned that, because you would have thought
that it's connected to the actual act of זריקה, zerika, but apparently
the גמרא Gemara chooses to say that if it's not the actual
placing, it's more of like the way to get it right up
to the placing, but you could have gone the other way, that's
not so much of interest to me. Maybe also the גמרא Gemara
likes to talk about it as הולכה holacha because הולכה holacha we
know there's a debate between the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon whether הולכה holacha is one of the עבודות avodot that thought
makes a difference since הולכה holacha doesn't have to be done and
the point is here it's a type of a הולכה holacha if
you would that has to be done. I understand, but anyway, but
it sort of since anyway one way or it doesn't matter, that's
what the גמרא's Gemara saying, anyway that that is debated. Okay. And
the question is is can you like insert a new עבודה avodah
that isn't one of the classic four. By a מנחה mincha we
have certain parallels, right? So you take the קומץ kometz of the
מנחה mincha that's like שחיטה, shechita, you put it in the כלי
kli that's like קבלה, kabbala, the גמרא Gemara says it's not exactly
קבלה, kabbala, you burn it on the altar that's like throwing the
blood on the altar, so there are parallels. But this isn't doesn't
have an exact parallel, so that's part of the question: can we
add an עבודה avodah even though yes it is a necessary עבודה
avodah and it's explicitly mentioned in the פסוק? pasuk? So that's what
the גמרא Gemara asks. So now we pick up at the bottom
of and it's debated, we had different opinions on either side. So
the גמרא Gemara on the bottom of י"ג עמוד ב' yud-gimmel amud-bet
says the following:
לימא כתנאי, leima k'tana-ei, let's say this is going like the debate
of תנאים: Tannaim: דתניא חדא, d'tanya chada, טבילת אצבע מפגלת בחטאת, t'vilas
etzba m'paggeles b'chatas, the one one ברייתא Baraita teaches that the dipping
of the finger can cause פיגול pigul in a חטאת. chatas. Okay
not only a חטאת, chatas, whatever, anyway if you're having a פיגול
pigul to eat it at the wrong time, that actually would make
it פיגול, pigul, that is an עבודה. avodah. ותניא אידך לא מפגלת,
v'tanya idach lo m'paggeles, it doesn't make פיגול, pigul, ולא מתפגלת. v'lo
mitpaggeles. If you're doing something else like you're שחיטה shechting it with
the intent to dip your finger in the blood, then it's also
not a an intent, it's not the content of the intent that
makes it פיגול pigul as well because as we turned talked earlier,
by the way that's only the things that are considered an אכילה.
achila. When you're doing an עבודה, avodah, you're thinking to an אכילה
שלא בזמנו, achila shelo bizmano, an אכילה achila is either the eating
of the altar, putting it on the altar, or when you are
going to eat it, okay, anyway, so the fact that it's ולא
מתפגלת v'lo mitpaggeles is not our interest, what's our interest is the
two different opinions of whether it's מפגלת, m'paggeles, whether the thought during
that time makes פיגול. pigul. So מאי לאו תנאי, mai lav tana-ei,
look, it's a straight debate of תנאים Tannaim whether the dipping of
the finger is one of the עבודות. avodot. So certainly the one
that says it's מפגלת m'paggeles says it's a central עבודה. avodah. The
question is if you have a way of bracketing the position that
says it's not מפגלת. m'paggeles. So let's take a look at what
the גמרא Gemara says: לא הא רבנן הא רבי שמעון. lo ha
Rabbanan ha Rabbi Shimon. No, it's a debate of רבנן Rabbanan and
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. For the רבנן Rabbanan it is an עבודה,
avodah, for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says הולכה... holacha... הולכה Holachah
*holacha* isn't an עבודה Avodah *avoda*, so I mean, but it is
not isn't an עבודה Avodah *avoda*, but isn't an עבודה Avodah, *avoda*
during which thought matters. So here too, this is not an עבודה
Avodah *avoda* during which your thought can invalidate.
I'm sorry, that is a תנאי *tenai* though, no? Wasn't רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon *rabbi Shimon* a תנא Tanna *tanna*? Yeah. So he says...
No, no, let's say it's a debate of even within the רבנן
Rabbanan. *rabbanan*'s position, even without problematizing הולכה Holachah *holacha*, it's a debate
whether this gets to count as הולכה holachah *holacha*. That's what we
want to know. And the answer is no, maybe everybody agrees that
it gets to count as הולכה holachah, *holacha* and it's really just
some bigger debate about what the story is about הולכה holachah *holacha*.
It's not a debate about the dipping of the finger, it's a
debate about הולכה holachah *holacha*. Of course the funny thing is, okay,
that with רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon *rabbi Shimon*, right, one of the
reasons רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon, *rabbi Shimon* says הולכה holacha *holacha* doesn't
count for this issue is because you could do without it. You
can't do without this. Anyway, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says here. Okay. מאי אי רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon מאי איריא
טבילת אצבע? האמר כל שאין על מזבח Mizbeach. החיצון כשלמים אינו בשום
פיגול pigul *Mai ee rabbi Shimon mai eerya tvilas etzba? Ha'amar kol
she'ein al mizbayach hachitzon kishlamim einu bishum pigul*. Wait a minute, if
it's רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *rabbi Shimon*, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *rabbi
Shimon* says that we're talking about an inner חטאת Chatas *chatas*, and
an inner חטאת Chatas? *chatas* is not offered on the outer altar.
And רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *rabbi Shimon* in פיגול pigul *pigul* has
a different position, not related to this position here of his, and
he just said anything that's not brought on the outer altar is
excluded from the laws of פיגול pigul? *pigul*. So obviously it's not
a רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon *rabbi Shimon*'s sort of position here, because
then he wouldn't get into the tiny details of the dipping of
the finger. Anything you do by an inner חטאת Chatas *chatas* doesn't
make פיגול pigul *pigul*. Okay? So even שחיטה shechitah, *shechita* doesn't make
פיגול pigul *pigul*, זריקה Zerikah *zerika* doesn't make פיגול pigul *pigul*, whatever.
So אלא הא והא רבנן Rabbanan *Ela ha veha rabbanan*. Fine, both
of them are working within the רבנן *rabbanan*'s position that הולכה holacha,
*holacha* is generally a, you know, מחשבה machshava *machshava* matters, thought matters.
So then is it a debate of תנאים Tannaim. *tannaim*? That it
seems like one says this counts as הולכה holacha *holacha*, one says
it doesn't. ולא קשיא *Velo kashya*. It's not difficult. Meaning not not
difficult, but you don't have to say it's a debate of תנאים
*tannaim*. I can say everybody holds the dipping of the finger מחשבה
machshava *machshava* matters. כאן בחטאת החיצונה כאן בחטאת הפנימית *Kan b'chatas hachitzona
kan b'chatas hapnimis*. The difference is the inner and the outer חטאת
Chatas *chatas*. By an inner חטאת Chatas, *chatas* where not only is
it necessary but it's explicitly labeled in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, there
everybody agree, there it is like הולכה holacha. *holacha* for the רבנן
*rabbanan* and thought matters. By the outer חטאת Chatas *chatas*, although it's
necessary, since it's not labeled by the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*, it doesn't
get to count as a new עבודה Avodah *avoda* or incorporated in
an old עבודה avodah *avoda*, and thought does not, will not invalidate
for an outer חטאת Chatas, *chatas*. Okay? Now, חטאת Chatas החיצונה פשיטא
*chatas hachitzona pshita*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks it's obvious. I don't
think it's obvious at all. You know, once it's necessary and so
on, how obvious is it that I should think it should matter
for the outer חטאת Chatas *chatas*? But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
פשיטא לא כתיב ביה וטבל *pshita lo ksiv bei vetaval*. It doesn't
say dip the finger. Okay. איצטריך *Itztrich*. No, you need to tell
me that it doesn't apply to the outer חטאת Chatas, *chatas*. סלקא
דעתך אמינא *Salka dach'tach amina*. I would have thought, הוה כתיב ולקח
*hava ksiv velakach*. It says he should he should take באצבעו מן
הדם *b'etzba'o min hadam*. It says he should take the blood with
his finger, which is pretty close to saying וטבל *vetaval*, dip it
in the blood. It says take it with your finger. And we
really interpret take it that that act is really required, it's not
just get it on your finger in some way. Okay, there really
is by the outer חטאת chatas, *chatas* the act of dipping is
actually required. How do you know that? דאי אתי קוף רמי ליה
אידיה *De'ee asi kof rami lei yadei*. Let's say a monkey comes,
who had a monkey loose in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis
HaMikdash*? A monkey comes and takes from the blood and puts it
on the כהן Kohen *kohen*'s finger, בעי למיטבל זימנא אחריתי *ba'ee l'mitbal
zimna achriti*. You have to dip your finger back into the blood.
It's not just that the blood is on the finger, actually by
the outer חטאת chatas? *chatas* as well, there's an act of dipping
the finger into the blood. So therefore, כמאן דכתיב de-chsiv, וטבל דמי
*k'man de'ksiv vetaval dami*. I might think that since that's what we
that's what we interpret the word to take and we say that
it actually is required to do an act of taking and an
act of dipping, so it's like it said explicitly and therefore by
an outer חטאת Chatas *chatas* it also should be a central עבודה
avoda *avoda*. קא משמע לן *Ka mashma lan*. Not, why not? להכי
לא כתיב וטבל דמשמע הכי ומשמע הכי *Lehachi lo ksiv vetaval d'mashma
hachi u'mashma hachi*. It didn't say וטבל *vetaval* to say that it's
not as central as it is by the inner חטאת chatas. *chatas*.
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* also points out that one of the things we
learn from the word ולקח *velakach* is we interpret it to not
emphasize ולקח באצבעו *velakach b'etzba'o*, take with your finger, we just emphasize
ולקח *velakach* the blood, take the blood. And we actually learn from
this that the idea of קבלה Kabbalah, *kabbala*, of, you know, catching
the blood in a vessel when the animal is slaughtered. Take the
blood means take it out of the neck of the animal, not
take it with your finger. So we sort of in one way
of reading this פסוק Pasuk. *pasuk* we bracket the word finger. So
therefore, because it doesn't say explicitly dip and because the word ולקח
*velakach* is used to also mean something else, catching the blood, although
הלכתית halachically *halachically* yes, it also means dip and that's how we
read it and that's a necessary act by the outer חטאת chatas
*chatas*, since the תורה Torah *Torah* does not explicitly refer to the
act, therefore we say that we're not going to add that as
an עבודה avoda? *avoda*, consider that an עבודה avoda *avoda* for which
thought matters. So now you have both by the inner and the
outer חטאת chatas *chatas* you need to dip it, if you don't
dip your finger in it's
invalid, okay, and therefore the but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says... That
the תורה Torah labeled it, then we're going to consider it to
be part of the עבודה Avodah. of הולכה holacha where thought matters,
and if it didn't label it like the outer חטאת chatas even
though it's necessary, it is not considered part of the עבודה Avodah.
of הולכה holacha and thought does not invalidate. Yes.
So I'm trying to understand, I thought, no, unless I'm wrong that...
That was your first mistake, that you're trying to understand. Go ahead,
yes.
Isn't this specifically for the חטאת נשיא Chatas Nasi though? This is...
No, well, it generalizes it.
So for every חטאת? chatas So like the זריקה really is really
the place... so you don't like...
Correct. Every חטאת chatas. you put it with on the corners of
the מזבח. Mizbeach. We'll get to that later. Okay, but yes, every
חטאת chatas is the either the corners of the outer altar with
a dipping or the corners of the inner.
And why does the גמרא Gemara, feel, I mean, that it can
learn this from נשיא Nasi if...
Whatever, we'll get to that later. That's not our topic now. רבי
שמעון מכשיר בהילוך. Rebbi Shimon machshir behiluch. So now we're going to
get to the רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon's which we've been referring to,
that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says that the act of transporting, although
it is an עבודה, Avodah? since it's an עבודה Avodah that you
could situate yourself in a place where you don't have to do
it, you can slaughter right by the side of the altar if
you wanted to, then even if you happen by circumstance to slaughter
it more distant from the altar, because it's not an עבודה Avodah?
that had to take place, thought during that does not invalidate. Okay.
Now,
אמר רבי שמעון לא, מודה רבי שמעון בהולכת חטאת הפנימית שמחשבה פוסלת
בו. Amar Rebbi Shimon lo, modeh Rebbi Shimon beholachas chatas hapnimis shemachshavah
poseles bo. Talking about the inner חטאת, chatas you can't slaughter an
inner חטאת chatas inside the actual עזרה. Azarah. Okay, now actually it's
an interesting question, who said not? If you look at רש״י, Rashi,
רש״י Rashi says it's not the דרך derech to do it, it
would be inappropriate. Inappropriate does not is not the same as הלכתית
halachically impossible. The גמרא Gemara makes it sound like it's more than
that, like if the תורה Torah says that you sort of, you
know, anyway, just to give you a quick, right? Here's the, right?
This is the אולם, Ulam, we're going to need this in a
minute. This is the היכל.
Heichal. You should have one of those always, they're so soft.
I know, I know.
More beef.
Okay, here's the מנורה, Menorah, here's the שולחן, Shulchan, here's the מזבח.
mizbe'ach Fine. We'll make it בידי שמים. biydei shamayim. Okay, anyway.
Am I doing it right?
No, the other way.
The other way.
That's
the ramp.
Wait, the ramp was...
No.
Where was it? It's like this, like that. Right. Okay, thank you.
Ooh,
3D.
Yeah, anyway. All right, so, anyway, there you go. So, this is,
so anyway, so the what do you call it, the,
so the assumption is, of course the תורה would never want you
to שחט shecht an animal inside here, but you're going to שחט
shecht it out here, you שחט shecht it at the north and
you're going to bring the blood to sprinkle the blood on the
inner altar. So because it is impossible presumably,
inappropriate slash impossible, to שחט shecht an animal inside the אולם Ulam
and the היכל, Heichal, it had to be slaughtered outside, and therefore
it had to be brought, and therefore that is a הולכה holacha,
that actually thought would invalidate.
Okay. But you actually can שחט shecht that inside, if then
like that's it, you got it. Well, that's not clear. רש״י Rashi
makes it might make it sound like it might actually be כשר,
kosher, but then the גמרא Gemara doesn't make as much sense. Okay,
so we're going to assume that it's not הלכתית halachically acceptable, although
רש״י Rashi just says it's not appropriate. It's not, it would, you
know, it obviously can't happen in a practical sense.
I would think it'd be very inappropriate.
I'm not disagreeing that it's inappropriate, I would but I would think
that for the גמרא Gemara to make sense it would have to
be הלכתית not valid. Okay.
Okay. מודה רבי שמעון בהולכת חטאת הפנימית שמחשבה פוסלת בו, Modeh Rebbi
Shimon beholachas chatas hapnimis shemachshavah poseles bo, right? Why? הואיל ועבודה שאינו
יכול לבטלה. Hoil ve'avodah she'eino yachol levatlah. You're going to have to
שחט shecht it outside and bring it inside. Okay. So, הואיל ושאינו
יכול לבטלה. Hoil veshe'eino yachol levatlah.
ואמר רבי שמעון כל שאינו על מזבח החיצון כשלמים אין חייבין עליו
משום פיגול. Ve'amar Rebbi Shimon kol she'eino al mizbeach hachitzon kishlamim ein
chayavin alav mishum pigul. One minute, says the גמרא, Gemara like we
said before. You might be right about that, but if we're talking
about an inner חטאת, chatas פיגול pigul is not relevant, because he
says פיגול pigul, is only relevant by things on the outer altar.
Now, pause. רש״י Rashi says the גמרא Gemara had a very easy
response. The easy response was, who says we're talking about פיגול? pigul
We're talking about a thought of שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah. Okay, that's
what our משנה mishnah is fundamentally focusing on, a thought of שלא
לשמה. shelo lishmah. Does it invalidate or so on? And that of
course we could say הולכה, holacha, bringing in the blood of an
inner חטאת chatas, into the inner, you know, into the היכל Heichal
is something that what do you call it, that had to happen,
it was a necessary עבודה Avodah and thought invalidates for שלא לשמה.
shelo lishmah. And the answer is yes, the גמרא Gemara could have
said that. Okay, but once, since it was framing it as, oh,
maybe does a פיגול piggul thought invalidate? Wait, a פיגול piggul thought
can't invalidate because פיגול piggul isn't relevant for an inner חטאת chatas
according to רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, we're going to answer within the
פיגול piggul context. But the easier answer would have been who says
we're talking about פיגול, piggul, we're talking about שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אמר רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא מודה היה לפסול מקל וחומר. Amar Rebbi Yosi berabbi
Chanina modeh hayah lifsol mikal vachomer.
Although רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. says that a פיגול piggul, is not
relevant to an inner חטאת, chatas it's not on the outer altar.
What he meant was that the meat does not become a status
of פיגול piggul if you're thinking to do it in the wrong
time and what's the status of פיגול piggul on the meat? If
you eat it you get כרת. kares. Okay, that's the point, if
you think to do it at the wrong time you not only
invalidate the sacrifice, the meat is considered פיגול piggul and if you
eat it you get כרת. kares. So when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
said פיגול piggul, is not relevant on inner חטאות, chataos, on things
that are not on the outer altar, all he meant was that
the leftover meat does not become פיגול, piggul. but he would agree
that it would have the power to invalidate the sacrifice.
The leftover meat from inner חטאות chataos which you're not supposed to
be eating anyway?
Right. So, but if you ate it anyway you'd be עובר over
on a לאו, lav, but you wouldn't get כרת. kares. If it's
also פיגול, piggul you get כרת. kares. Okay, so רבי שמעון'ס Rebbe
Shimon's point to say פיגול piggul, is not relevant
means that the status of פיגול piggul. on the meat doesn't take
hold to get כרת kares for eating it, but it does not
mean that a thought of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano doesn't invalidate. The
same way a thought of שלא לשמו shelo lishmo invalidates, a thought
of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano invalidates. Okay, so that's a nice distinction.
מודה היה לפסול מקל וחומר. modeh haya lifsol mikal vachomer. ומה שלא
לשמן שהוכשרו בשלמים פסול בחטאת, umah shelo lishman shehuchshru bishlamim pasul bachatat,
חוץ לזמנו שפסול בשלמים אינו דין שיפסול בחטאת. chutz lizmano shepasul bishlamim
eino din sheyifsol bachatat. If you have a thought of שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo which doesn't invalidate a שלמים, shlamim, okay, and it does
invalidate a חטאת, chatas a thought of eating it at the wrong
time, a פיגול piggul, thought, which it does invalidate by a שלמים,
shlamim, how much more so should it invalidate by a חטאת? chatas
Very logical קל וחומר. kal vachomer. חטאת chatas. is easier to invalidate
than a שלמים, shlamim, and if חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano invalidates a
שלמים shlamim it should invalidate a חטאת. Maybe it's not פיגול, pigul
but it should invalidate the קרבן. korban. So גמרא Gemara says like
this: הניחא חוץ לזמנו. haniacha chutz lizmano. Now that's חוץ לזמנו, chutz
lizmano, a thought invalidates even by an inner חטאת that doesn't have
פיגול. pigul חוץ למקומו מנלן? chutz limkomo minalan? How do you know
by חוץ למקומו? chutz limkomo? Again, if an inner חטאת is not
in the normal פיגול pigul category, where do you learn that a
thought of the wrong place invalidates the same way a שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo and a thought of the wrong time invalidates? אי מחוץ
לזמנו, ei michutz lizmano, if you're going to say well, just like
חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano invalidates, חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo invalidates because they're
sort of always seen as a package, wrong time, wrong place. Okay,
no. מה לחוץ לזמנו שכן כרת. mah lachutz lizmano sheken kares. חוץ
לזמנו Chutz lizmano is worse, maybe in this case there's not כרת
kares because it doesn't make the meat פיגול, pigul but in general
it has the power in other cases to turn something into פיגול.
So just because it can invalidate an inner חטאת doesn't mean the
thought of the wrong place can invalidate. אי משלא לשמו, ei mishelo
lishmo, okay, why don't we do the same קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
If שלא לשמו shelo lishmo invalidates a חטאת and שלא לשמו shelo
lishmo doesn't invalidate other things, certainly a thought of the wrong place
which invalidates other things should certainly invalidate a חטאת. That's reasonable. No,
no, there you could say no, because there's a way in which
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo has broader application than חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo,
the wrong place. Why? שכן נוהג בבמה. sheken noheg bivama. When you
are slaughter in a time when there's no בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash
it's interesting that this could be seen as a relevant factor. At
the time when there's no בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you bring
your sacrifices on these individual altars, okay, a thought of שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo would still invalidate.
Whereas חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo won't because you're already חוץ למקומו. chutz
limkomo. There's no sense of any particular מקום. makom. You can do
it in any place. Yeah, it's simply irrelevant. אי אפשר. ei efshar.
It's not like it's halachically, it's just you don't have the circumstance.
Right, so the whole fact that that could be a question is
bizarre. But then you can't learn out from שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
that certainly the thought of a wrong place should invalidate because a
wrong place doesn't have the same scope as שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo.
So the גמרא Gemara. says one minute, no, you actually can learn
it out because שלא לשמו shelo lishmo also doesn't apply by a
במה. bama. Why does שלא לשמו shelo lishmo not apply by a
במה? bama? שלא לשמן במאי נוהג, shelo lishman bemai noheg, where does
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo invalidate? Because that's what we're talking about, really
invalidating. בפסח וחטאת, befesach vechatat, by a פסח Pesach and a sin
offering. That's where שלא לשמו shelo lishmo really invalidates. פסח וחטאת בבמה
לא קרבו. pesach vechatat bivama lo karvu. You don't bring them on
a במה. bama. You only bring on a במה bama freewill sacrifices.
You don't bring obligatory sacrifices. So actually there's no חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo on a במה bama because there's no particular place and there's
no שלא לשמו shelo lishmo that invalidates because you're never bringing a
חטאת or a פסח Pesach to begin with. So actually you can
learn it, the same way שלא לשמו shelo lishmo invalidates you know
a חטאת and שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is a weaker, it doesn't
invalidate a שלמים. shlamim. So the thought of the wrong place should
certainly invalidate even an inner חטאת because that
invalidates all things, the thought of a wrong time and a thought
of a wrong place. So even though רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
an inner חטאת doesn't become פיגול, the thought of wrong place or
wrong time does invalidate. And therefore we can say that when you
are bringing the blood inside by an inner חטאת, the הלכה halacha
is a necessary act and therefore the thought actually
does invalidate. Yes, David, you had a question?
Yeah, also are they suggesting that there was
a dominant chief from...
Oh
well you could bring a free will sacrifice
but whether atonement in the sense of a
חטאת the answer is no that obligatory things you don't bring on
the outer one. ואי בעית אימא V'ee ba'it eima if you want
I could say how do you know to learn how do you
know that it applies to not only the wrong place but the
wrong time but also the wrong place? היקשא הוא. Hekesha hu.
We learn out from the פסוק Pasuk, that same time and same
place have the same הלכה halachah so even though
same thing I mean wrong time is weightier since the verse links
them you learn one from the other. Where does the verse link
them? It says אם האכל יאכל ביום השלישי פיגול הוא לא ירצה.
Im he'achol ye'achel bayom hashlishi pigul hu lo yeratzeh. If it will
be eaten on the third day it is פיגול it will not
be desired and we say it means if you have a thought
to eat it on the third day. שלישי Shlishi third day is
חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zemano means a thought to eat it in the
wrong time that's what it means.
פיגול הוא לא ירצה Pigul hu lo yeratzeh it's פיגול it won't
be accepted that's a little redundant why did you have to say
that? זה חוץ למקומו Ze chutz l'mekomo that includes as a thought
of the wrong place which is ironic because the הלכה halachah of
פיגול is only the wrong time it's quite ironic. But anyway bottom
line is the verse sort of packages together with through the rabbinic
reading of the verse we package together wrong time and wrong place
and therefore we say that what do you call it that that
that the same way a thought of a wrong time invalidates a
thought of a wrong place invalidates so even for רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon that an inner חטאת does not become פיגול the thought does
invalidate. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara, is going to have fun.
Now that we're done with that problem of the inner חטאת we're
going to have fun figuring out how much of the walking is
actually necessary. Where exactly could you slaughter it? How close could you
slaughter it? So which amount of the walking is necessary?
Okay you have the כבש kevesh on the north.
Yeah that's what I thought. See Michael you distracted me you confused
me. The כבש kevesh goes down to the south right? I was
right the first time. See last time I thought that I was
mistaken I was wrong. Okay anyway.
So that means you got to move the מזבח mizbe'ach up then?
No the מזבח mizbe'ach sort of goes sort of there's a question
where the מזבח mizbe'ach ends. Does it end exactly in the middle
point or does it end whatever? But anyway yeah I was right
the first time. Okay fine.
Okay anyway. Okay so all
right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Thank you Dave.
Okay I was going to check that as that was up there
I was saying to myself that looks wrong that's not right. So
anyway okay. So anyway you don't believe Michael?
Get out a show you it's fine it's fine. Oh here
fine
here.
We should have this out anyway.
That's a good picture.
See? So the כבש kevesh goes down there. All right
anyway. All right. So now let's go on. The גמרא Gemara says
like this. All right. Now now we're going to have fun. Okay.
אמר רבא Amar Rava אם תמצי לומר im timtzi lomar רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon סבר לה כברי Savar lah k'Brei דאמר בינו לאולם למזבח
צפון. d'amar beino l'ulam l'mizbe'ach tzafon Now you have to slaughter this
inner חטאת at the north of the altar. So we would think
it would mean you have to slaughter it here okay and that
the necessary הולכה holacha because if it can't
it has to be north of the altar like this would be
the closest you could get. Anywhere beyond that is not on the
side of the altar. So the necessary הולכה Holacha would be you
know all of this walking. Okay but he says one minute but
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon son says that even if it's not opposite
the altar itself
even if it's here it's the north of the altar it's in
this space between the אולם ulam and the מזבח Mizbe'ach so it's
not it's like closer to the holier place okay and it's to
the north this space this air space counts as slaughtering it to
the north of the altar. So if this air space counts as
slaughtering it to the north of the altar you can slaughter it
right up to there. So where's the necessary walking? Okay so let's
take a look. Okay so even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon where were
we? סבר לה savar lah כברי k'Brei דאמר d'amar בינו לאולם למזבח
צפון beino l'ulam l'mizbe'ach tzafon. it's considered north even if it's not
directly opposite the altar. אין מחשבה מועלת בו בהולכת חטאת הפנימית אלא
מפתח אולם ולפנים. Ein machshavah mo'eles bo b'holachas chatas hapnimiyos ela mipisach
ulam v'lifnim. Only from the door of the אולם ulam where assume
you can't slaughter it inside this building okay so the only necessary
walking because you could have slaughtered it right at the door so
the only necessary walking is from the door going in. ואם תמצי
לומר V'im timtzi lomar now we're having this is like a lot
of fun you can tell the גמרא. Gemara ואם תמצי לומר V'im
timtzi lomar סבר לה כרבי יהודה savar lah k'Rebbe Yehuda דאמר תוך
עזרה מקדש d'amar toch azarah mikadesh אין מחשבה מועלת בו בהולכת סילוק
בזיכין. ein machshavah mo'eles bo b'holachas siluk bezichin. Now we're going to
move away from the inner חטאת. There's another question which is... Okay,
there's a position that says that the floor here has the—the floor
between the אולם Ulam and the מזבח has the same sanctity of
the altar. And something that is supposed to be burnt on the
altar, not that you can sprinkle the blood, you need the physical
altar to sprinkle the blood. But something that's supposed to be burnt
on the altar, you can make a little fire and you could
burn it in this floor space right here. So, what is a
type of a thing whose עבודה Avodah. is to be brought to
be burnt?
Well, it's the קומץ kometz of the מנחה, mincha, okay, but
that maybe you could do right up against it, so there would
be, you know, whatever. No, he's supposed to burn the קטורת. Ketoret.
Okay, ah, so what we're going to say is, what, okay, but
fine, but we're talking about something that also like has a מתיר
matir and whatever. So we're talking about you take the incense of
the bread and you have to bring it out here and you
burn it on the altar, that allows the bread to be eaten.
So, at what stage, what walking is necessary? So we're going to
say as soon as you leave the אולם, Ulam, any more walking
to the altar isn't necessary because if you wanted to at least
in theory you could burn it as soon as you got out
of the אולם, Ulam, okay, and you could burn it right there.
So the only walking that's necessary is getting to the door of
the אולם. Ulam. Now, okay, so he says like
this: אמר תוך עזרה מקדש Amar toch azarah mekadesh אין מחשבה מועלת
בלא הילוך לסילוק בזיכין ein machshava mo'eles belo hillocha le-siluk bezichin removing
the incense from the from the bread
אלא מפתח היכל ולחוץ. ella mi-petach Heichal velachutz. Now, he says the
only necessary walking is from the door of the היכל. Heichal. Why
from the door of the היכל? Heichal? What? I don't understand, you
have to walk from the altar to the door. Isn't that walking
necessary? Right? Why is it only the door of the היכל? Heichal?
This is the door of the היכל. Heichal. Why is only that
walking, maybe I'll make that in blue, okay?
This is the door of the היכל. Heichal. So why does he
say this is the only walking that's necessary? Because you could burn
it right here. Don't you have to walk it from the altar
to the door? And the answer is no, because in theory, you
could put that altar right up against the door and it would
still be כשר kosher placement of that altar, the inner altar. So
even though it happens to be placed here, that walking is in
theory not necessary, because in theory this could be right up against
the door. And in theory you could burn it right here. So
the only necessary walking is from the door of the היכל Heichal
to the door to the door of the אולם. Ulam. Alright, so
now we
continue. ואם תמצא לומר, Ve'im timtza lomar, okay, ואם תמצא לומר סבר
קדושת היכל ואולם חדא היא. Ve'im timtza lomar savar kedushas Heichal ve-Ulam
chada hi. Now, let's say they held that actually the היכל Heichal
and the אולם Ulam had one sanctity. Okay, and if it has
one sanctity then it means that in theory the altar could be
not only right up to the door of the of the היכל
Heichal but right up to the door of the אולם. Ulam. If
this is all considered one, you know, one level, so if you
and in theory this could be anywhere in the היכל, Heichal, so
in theory it could be right up to the door of the
אולם. Ulam. So if that's true, what walking is necessary? The only
walking that's necessary is getting from the edge of the אולם Ulam
to right out of the אולם Ulam to the, you know, to
the to the floor of the עזרה. Azarah. So ואם תמצא לומר
סבר קדושת היכל ואולם חדא היא אין מחשבה
מועלת אלא מפתח אולם ולחוץ. Ve'im timtza lomar savar kedushas Heichal ve-Ulam
chada hi ein machshava mo'eles ella mi-petach Ulam velachutz. So where is
that walking? So the walking is is that there was actually, here's
your 3D, okay, there was actually thickness to the opening. It was
a thick wall basically. So here was the door, okay, and here
was like the floor, right, of the here's the floor of the
עזרה. Azarah.
This is the עזרה Azarah and this is the door of the
אולם. Ulam. Okay, that's the door of the אולם. Ulam. So there's
actually thickness in that door. So the אולם Ulam ends here. Okay,
and in theory the altar could only be right up to the
doorway. And the עזרה Azarah right you you go through a thick
like a thick wall, like you know everyone walks through like the
gates you know the the the Jaffa Gate or whatever, you know,
there's like it's like a few feet, okay, you walk through it
and then you get to the עזרה. Azarah. So the only place
that you have to because the altar couldn't be here and you
can only offer it in theory on the floor here. So the
only necessary walking was through that thickness of the opening. Okay, so
אלא מפתח אולם ולחוץ. ella mi-petach Ulam velachutz. ואם תמצא לומר תוך
פתח, Ve'im timtza lomar toch petach,
so the only walking would be from the from the you know
from the doorway of it to getting outside through the width of
the doorway. ואם תמצא לומר הפתח כלפנים. Ve'im timtza lomar hapetach kelifnim.
Now one minute, maybe the thickness of the of the opening counts
like the actual אולם Ulam itself. So in theory you actually could
have the
incense altar right up against the edge of the outer door. So
if that's true, you could take in theory you could I mean
not the incense altar, it was actually we're talking here about the
what do you call it? About the oh, I mentioned the altar
before, I meant the שולחן. Shulchan. Okay, but anyway, the same point.
Okay, you could bring the you could the שולחן Shulchan or whatever
could be right up any of these things could be right up
against the edge. So in theory... You could have the שולחן Shulchan
right up against the edge of the outer of the door to
the אולם, Ulam, and all you would have to do, here I
am, I'm standing, I have the שולחן Shulchan right here, I took
the incense, okay, and the only thing that I have to do
is stick my hand out and burn it on the floor. I
don't even have to take a step out. Okay, so if the
floor of the עזרה Azarah has the sanctity of the altar, and
in theory you could burn things on this floor right here, and
the שולחן Shulchan can be anywhere the היכל Heichal in theory, so
in theory and if the אולם Ulam has the same sanctity of
the היכל Heichal and the door of the אולם Ulam has the
same sanctity of the היכל, Heichal, then you could bring the, then
in theory the שולחן Shulchan could be brought right up to the
outer edge of the doorway here. So any walking of those of
those little you know spoons of frankincense is in theory not necessary
because in theory this could have been right up at the edge
of the door and the only necessary traveling of that incense is
from the edge of the door to placing it down on the
floor. Okay, that would be the only time that a מחשבה machshava
could invalidate. Okay, so because it's for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon that
is the only necessary transporting that has to take place. אלא בכדי
להושיט ידו ולפנים. Ela bichedei lehoshit yado ulifnim.
ואם תמצא לומר תוך פתח כלפנים, Ve-im timtza lomar toch petach kelifnim,
אין מחשבה מועלת אפילו פסיעה אחת, ein machshava mo'eles afilu pesiah achas,
not even one step. The only thing it would be would be
the stretching of the arm, the going from the edge to the
putting it down. Okay. ואם תמצא לומר תוך Ve-im timtza lomar toch
wait, wait, אלא בכדי
הושטת ידו, ela bichedei hoshitas yado, just the act of stretching your
arm down, that's that distance, okay, that would be the only sort
of you know place in which מחשבה machshava could matter. ואם תמצא
לומר סבר הולכה שלא ברגל לא שמה הולכה, Ve-im timtza lomar savar
halacha shelo beregel lo shemah halacha, and now we're about to, this
is going to introduce the new topic. Is when you transport it
without your leg, if you just did, if you just, you know,
let's say you imagine you got the כהנים Kohanim lined up and
everybody just handed it from one to the next and nobody moved,
is that considered an act of הולכה Holacha or not? That's going
to be a debate. If it's not considered an act of הולכה,
Holacha. so then there's no act of הולכה Holacha. that invalidates here.
אין מחשבה מועלת כלל. Ein machshava mo'eles klal. Then, then מחשבה Machshava
would not invalidate at all because the only thing that would invalidate
would be the act of putting it down and that might not
halakhically be defined as an act of הולכה. Holacha. That might just,
so okay, so therefore we've got this, okay, so therefore the point
is is that only necessary הולכה holacha invalidates and now we've had
fun figuring out what is necessary הולכה holacha for רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon, The taking of the incense here, this traveling is not necessary
because the שולחן Shulchan can be up to the door of the
היכל, Heichal, maybe up to the door of the אולם, Ulam, maybe
even in the door of the אולם, Ulam, and if the floor
has the sanctity of the altar, which is also
debatable, then there's absolutely no traveling by walking that is necessary. Okay.
So now the גמרא, Gemara this
now we get into a,
now we're going to explore again these issues about הולכה, holacha, about
how since it's something that could be like done away with in
theory based, you know, so how central is it as an עבודה?
Avodah. And then we're also going to get to issues about הולכה
שלא ברגל. holacha shelo beregel. So let's take a look. אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, three lines from the bottom. אמר ליה אביי
לאמוריה דרב חסדא. Amar lei Abaye le-amoria de-Rav Chisda. Abaye said to
his, to the אמורא Amora of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. The אמורא
Amora was, you know, we sometimes speak an אמורא, Amora, אביי Abaye
is an אמורא, Amora, רב חסדא Rav Chisda is an אמורא, Amora,
you know, and a תנא Tanna, we think, oh, רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir is a תנא, Tanna. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is a תנא.
Tanna But it's like what I sometimes refer to as a big
T תנא Tanna and a lowercase תנא Tanna or a capital A
אמורא Amora and a lowercase אמורא. Amora. The capital T תנא Tanna
is רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, רבי עקיבא. Rebbi
Akiva. The lowercase T תנא is the guy whose job it was
was to just memorize all of the teachings and say them over,
the walking book, which is what you had in an oral culture.
Now, the אמורא, Amora, since by the אמוראים, amoraia, you know, they
did not have their teachings, you know, it wasn't as much, I
mean, it was more discussion or whatever, it wasn't as much like
a collection of memorized teachings, I mean, it was but not the
same as the תנאים. The role of the lowercase A אמורא Amora
was to be like the announcer. Okay, so I was giving a
שיעור, shiur, I don't want to strain my voice and we don't
have any microphones or whatever, I tell my אמורא Amora what to
say and he goes ahead and he like, he's the one that
projects it to the whole audience. Okay, that's what an אמורא Amora
was. So אביי Abaye said to the אמורא Amora of רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, בעי מיניה רב חסדא, ba'ei minei Rav Chisda, next time
you see רב חסדא Rav Chisda ask him the following question. הולכה
בזר מהו. Holacha bezar mahu. If you have a non-כהן Kohen do
the הולכה, holacha, what's the הלכה? halacha? Normally a non-כהן Kohen does
the עבודה Avodah. it's פסול, pasul, but for example, we have the
case of שחיטה, shechitah slaughtering, which can be כשר kasher by a
non-כהן Kohen. because as the גמרא Gemara says by a clear, you
know, just a close attention to the פסוקים, pesukim, it only mentions
the כהנים Kohanim after describing slaughtering it. It never talks about the
כהנים Kohanim to be the one to slaughter it. So slaughtering is
שחיטה כשרה בזר, shechitah kesherah bezar, it can be done by a
non-כהן. Kohen, So even though שחיטה shechitah as we know is one
of the עבודות, avodos, if you have a מחשבה Machshava during שחיטה
Shechita it invalidates and so on. So here too, since הולכה holacha,
is more נגע nege Suppose, even though it occurs after the קבלה,
Kabbalah and the קבלה kabbala needs a כהן, Kohen right, so you
might think once you start needing כהנים, Kohanim, it's as they say
turtles all the way down, it's כהנים Kohanim all the way down,
right, once you start needing a כהן Kohen maybe you think you
can't, but he says maybe not. הולכה holacha is this sort of
weirder עבודה. Avodah, What's the story about if a non-כהן Kohen does
it? So אמר ליה Amar lei כשירה, Keshera, it's kosher, ומקרא מסייעני
Umikra mesayeni and I got a פסוק Pasuk to support me. וישחטו
את הפסח Vayishchatu es hapesach in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim they slaughtered
the פסח Pesach and who's slaughtering? The people. ויזרקו הכהנים את הדם
מידם Vayizreku hakohanim es hadam miyadam and the כהנים Kohanim threw the
blood from their hands, presumably the hands of the slaughterers.
So the people
who slaughtered were the ones who actually then brought the blood to
the כהנים Kohanim and the כהנים Kohanim threw it. So רש"י says
you have to assume that there was a כהן Kohen who caught
the blood, but okay, I slaughter, a כהן Kohen catches the blood,
I can't slaughter and catch the blood all at the same time.
And then the כהן Kohen who caught the blood hands it to
me and I'll bring it to the כהן Kohen. who's going to
throw the blood, it's actually probably an efficient type process because I'm
done, you know, I'm free now after I'm done slaughtering, let me
be the one to bring the blood to the כהן. Kohen והלוים
מפשיטים Vehalviyim mafshitim and the כהנים Kohanim would flay it. So look,
you see that the normal people would bring the blood to the
כהנים. Kohanim. מתיבי רב ששת, Maseivei Rav Sheshes, Rav Sheshes, that's all
very nice you got a פסוק. Pasuk But you know, I got
a תניא אידך. Tanya idach. זר ואונן Zar ve'onen a non-כהן Kohen
and a somebody who immediately suffered a death, an אונן, Onen, שיכור
Shikor or somebody who's drunk, ובעל מום Ubaal mum or somebody who
has a
blemish, בקבלה בהולכה ובזריקה פסול. Bekabbalah beholacha uvizrika pasul. They invalidate whether
it's the catching of the blood, the transporting or the throwing. The
only thing they don't invalidate is שחיטה Shechita. because a non-כהן Kohen
can do the שחיטה. Shechita So it's explicit that הולכה holacha, a
non-כהן Kohen invalidates.
וכן יושב וכן שמאל. Vechen yoshev vechen smol. Similarly by the way
if you're sitting because it says לעמוד לשרת, Laamod leshares, so service
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash has to be standing and similarly
if it's with your left hand. There goes all of us lefties.
Okay, anyway.
תיופתא. Tyufta. That's a pretty explicit contradiction. What more do you need
than a ברייתא Braisa that explicitly says a זר Zar is invalid
for הולכה. holacha So והא רב חסדא קרא קאמר, Veha Rav Chisda
kra kaamar, it's very nice you got a תניא אידך Tanya idach
teaching but we certainly do have a פסוק, Pasuk that's supposed to
be authoritative. So the גמרא Gemara says no, דעביד מעשה אצטבא. De'avid
maaseh itztaba. The פסוק Pasuk. is talking about that the non-כהן Kohen
just acted like a like a pedestal. So what does that mean?
The כהן Kohen catches the blood, here I am, I'm standing like
this at, well okay, I slaughter it. So there's a כהן Kohen
catching the blood, then I move to this side of the כהן
Kohen and I just go like this, I put my hands out
and he puts the blood on my hands and then comes the
other כהן Kohen who's throwing it and he takes the blood from
my hands and he throws it. So I am actually just doing
an act of a pedestal, I'm not actually transporting it, okay, and
therefore that's kosher because it wasn't actual הולכה. holacha, Okay. Don't understand,
say that again.
No, a כלי.
Kli. The כהן Kohen catches it, right? Right. So I slaughter, shhh,
and the כהן Kohen catches it in this vessel and here's the
כלי Kli and he puts the vessel on my hands and comes
along another כהן Kohen and he takes it from my hands. And
that actually works in the פסוק because the פסוק says the כהנים
Kohanim took it from their hands. It doesn't say that they handed
it to the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, so that's how you can read
it in the פסוק. A non-כהן Kohen, could be doing an act
of a pedestal, all he's doing is he's just going like this,
he's like he's completely immobile, he's not actually transporting it. Okay. So
the גמרא gemara says like this. רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו. Rabba
veRav Yosef de'amri tarvaihu. Okay, so now it seems like there's a
clear ברייתא, Braisa, but the גמרא gemara is not done. רבה ורב
יוסף Rabba veRav Yosef both say
הולכה בזר מחלוקת רבי שמעון ורבנן. Holacha bezar machlokes Rabbi Shimon verabbanan.
It's actually tied into the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. and
the רבנן. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in general downgrades הולכה. holacha, Okay.
רבי שמעון דאמר עבודה שאפשר לבטלה לאו עבודה היא. Rabbi Shimon de'amar
avodah she'efshar levatla lav avodah hi. Since in theory you could do
away with it, it doesn't have the weight of an עבודה. Avodah,
And now the question is: does he really mean it's not an
עבודה? avoda. It's not enough of an עבודה avoda? that מחשבה Machshava
invalidates. That's an interesting general question. What is meant by whether you
label something as an עבודה? avoda שחיטה shchita is an עבודה avoda
and it can be done by a non-כהן, Kohen. right? But anyway,
so we'll sort of worry about that. But anyway, but I would
not have said that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. is saying it's not
an עבודה. avoda, Was that the language in the משנה? Mishna? I
would just have said that he said that מחשבה machshava doesn't invalidate.
What did he say?
שהיה אומר אי אפשר בשחיטה אבל
אפשר בהולכה. Shehayah omer iy efshar beshchita aval efshar beholacha. Yeah, he
just says it's possible to do without it, okay, and that מחשבה
machshava doesn't invalidate. But the גמרא gemara frames it that according to
him it's not an עבודה. avoda So for him who since he
basically says since you can do without it, I would just say
he downgrades it significantly, but the גמרא gemara says he considers it
not an עבודה. avoda. So once it's not an עבודה, avoda. it
can be done by a non-כהן. Kohen כשירה בזר. Keshera bezar. לרבנן
פסולה Lerabbanan pesula and the רבנן would say no, I'm sorry, it
still remains, it still has the full weight and you know, the
same way thought invalidates, it's a full עבודה, avoda. full weight, and
a non-כהן kohen would invalidate. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so
Abaye says wait, I got a... get that point that they have
to give different weights to הלכה. halacha. But the question about whether
you, you know, about the correlation you wanted to say with can
you do without it and can a non-כהן kohen. do it, is
not a correlation and it's not you can't bring it in. How
do you know it's not a correlation? שחיטה דעבודה שאי אפשר לבטלה,
shchita d'avoda she'i efshar levatla, שחיטה shchita you can't do without וכשרה
בזר, v'ksheira b'zar, and a זר zar can do it. So therefore,
look, there's no correlation between whether you need it and whether a
זר zar can do it. Okay? שחיטה shchita you need and a
זר zar can do. So you could also say the reverse, something
else you don't need and a זר zar can't do, like there's
no correlation. Okay?
So the גמרא gemara says, אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said
back to him, no, שחיטה לאו עבודה היא. shchita lav avoda hi.
שחיטה shchita is not an עבודה. avoda. That's why I said like
it's so, what do you mean by the word עבודה? avoda Like,
this is like a regular, you know, עבודה avoda, should suggest certain
הלכות halachos apply to it and not other הלכות. halachos. Like it's
always an interesting question to try to pin down exactly what cluster
of הלכות, halachos, because שחיטה shchita is obviously necessary for the קרבן
korban and מחשבה machshava invalidates and if you do it for עבודה
זרה avoda zara you're חייב מיתה chayav misa and if you do
it outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. you're חייב chayav for שחוטי
חוץ, shchutei chutz, but it's not an עבודה avoda, because it can
be done by a non-כהן. kohen. So now it's seemingly like we're
actually saying that the best test, I didn't say that, right, it
didn't say that. Correct, it didn't say that, that's correct. But that
is the most obvious thing that would position it as a non-עבודה,
avoda. you know, would or be a sign that it's a non-עבודה
avoda? is that it can be done by a non-כהן. kohen But
anyway, so what the גמרא gemara is saying like this: שחיטה shchita
is not an עבודה. avoda? So therefore, the fact that a זר
zar can do it is because it's not an עבודה. avoda But
הולכה holacha is an עבודה. avoda. You know, maybe the basic just
rule is you know from קבלה kabbala onwards is an עבודה. avoda
So הולכה holacha? is an עבודה avoda. and I'm going to say
that something that is an עבודה, avoda whether you need a כהן
kohen. or not, is a function of whether you can do without
it. שחיטה shchita, has its own laws. It's not an עבודה, avoda
you can't do without it, it can be done with a non-כהן.
kohen, Don't worry about שחיטה, shchita it's a weird thing, it's not
an עבודה. avoda. But once you start with the real עבודות avodos
from קבלה onwards, okay, then actually if it's then I will say
there is a correlation. If it's for ר' שמעון Reb Shimon who
downgrades הולכה, holacha, it can be done with a זר, zar, and
for the חכמים chachamim who don't downgrade הולכה, holacha? it cannot be
done with a זר. zar. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like
this,
ולאו, v'lo, are you telling me that שחיטה shchita is not an
עבודה? avoda דאמר רב זירא אמר רב, de-amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav,
שחיטת פרה בזר פסולה. shchitas parah b'zar psula. If you שחט shecht
the פרה אדומה parah adumah with a non-כהן, kohen. it's invalid. Okay,
ואמר רב עלה, v'amar Rav aloh, אלעזר וחקת כתיבא, Eleazar v'chukka ksiva,
because it says, you know, אלעזר Eleazar should take the פרה אדומה
parah adumah and says זאת חקת התורה, zos chukkas hatorah, so חקה
chukka means it has to be done exactly this way. Of course
we can't, you know, resuscitate, whatever, you
know, revivify אלעזר, Eleazar, so same means a כהן. kohen. He's not
a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, so okay, it has to be done
by a כהן. kohen When it says ושחט אלעזר הכהן, v'shachat Eleazar
hakohen, it means a כהן kohen has to שחט. shecht. So there's
a requirement that שחיטה shchita of the פרה אדומה parah adumah be
done with it. So how does that prove that it's an עבודה?
avoda? That's bizarre. Why? Because there's one thing that requires a כהן
kohen. presumably, but all the other שחיטות shechitos don't require a כהן.
kohen. So it's very strange, which is what the גמרא gemara is
going to sort of respond back. Oh, שחיטה shchita is an עבודה
avoda because there's one place, פרה אדומה, parah adumah, where it requires
a כהן. kohen, So that shows you it's an עבודה. avoda So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, שאני פרה דקדשי בדק הבית היא.
shani parah d'kadshai bedek habayis hi. פרה parah is not even a
קרבן, korban, it's not even relevant to the discussion. That's the funny
thing about פרה, parah, it's not brought in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. It has sanctity, it's not really קרבן korban sanctity, it's completely
irrelevant. It has this requirement, it needs a כהן, kohen, that's not
relevant for our general understanding of how does שחיטה shchita function in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash? So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
ולאו קל וחומר הוא? v'lav kal v'chomer hu? One minute, isn't it
a קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? קדשי בדק הבית הוי עבודה, kadshai bedek
habayis hava avoda, if by something that's not even a קרבן, korban,
it's considered an עבודה avoda. to require a כהן, kohen because now
the גמרא Gemara is saying any time it would require a כהן
kohen is a sign that it's an עבודה. avoda, So what do
you and somehow how do you explain all the other שחיטות shechitos
that a non-כהן kohen can do it? I don't know, it's an
עבודה avoda with exceptions. But, you know, sometimes it's an עבודה avoda.
that can be done by a זר. zar. But the fact that
sometimes a כהן kohen, is demanded is a sign that it must
be considered an עבודה. avoda. So if outside by by something that's
not a קרבן korban it's an עבודה avoda, because it requires a
כהן, kohen קדשי מזבח לאו עבודה היא? kadshai mizbeach lav avoda hi?
Would it, how could you say that by something that's a sacrifice
it wouldn't be an עבודה? avoda. So the גמרא Gemara wants to
say שחיטה shechita is an עבודה avoda because sometimes it requires a
כהן kohen and that's enough to prove that it's an עבודה avoda.
even if most of the time there's an exception. Okay, it has
special rules. אמר רב ששת בריה דרב אידי, amar Rav Sheshet brei
d'Rav Idi, no, that's not true. Just because something requires a כהן
kohen does not prove that it's an עבודה. avoda. I'll give you
something else ritual, can you think of it before we read the
next line? What ritual act requires a כהן Kohen, that is not
an עבודה, avoda that has nothing to do with the בית המקדש?
Beis Hamikdash Inspecting the spots of leprosy. Excellent. מידי דהוה אמראי נגעים,
midi d'hava
amarei
negaim, just like inspecting the spots of leprosy.
The what, for in?
What'd you say?
It's כהנים. kohanim.
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah, דלאו עבודה היא ובעי כהונה. delav avoda hi
ubaye kehuna. It's not an עבודה avoda and it requires כהונה. kehuna.
So yes, פרה אדומה para aduma is not relevant to a discussion
of the role of שחיטה shechita? by sacrifices. פרה אדומה para aduma
is not a sacrifice and the fact that you need a כהן,
Kohen sometimes you need כהן Kohen by non-sacrificial rituals. Okay, that is
not a proof of its status as an עבודה. avoda So it's
interesting that the גמרא Gemara wanted to say the fact that something
requires a כהן Kohen should be a signal that it's an עבודה.
avoda, So we have like how do we get our head around
שחיטה? shechita It's כשר בזר. kosher bezar. Do we say that so
now it really does seem if it's כשר בזר kosher bezar that
tells us that it's not an עבודה, avoda. if it requires a
כהן Kohen it tells us it is an עבודה. avoda, So the
גמרא Gemara seems to, it hasn't said it explicitly, but seems to
be thinking that the question of whether it's an עבודה avoda, is
a function of whether a כהן Kohen can do it or a
non-כהן Kohen can do it. So anyway שחיטה shechita put aside, okay,
because yes שחיטה's necessary and it could be זר, zar, but it's
not an עבודה. avoda, We want to know הולכה, holacha. which presumably
is an עבודה. avoda. Should we therefore say that since רבי שמעון
downgrades it as an עבודה—the avoda גמרא Gemara actually phrases it לאו
עבודה היא—since lav avoda hi he downgrades it, should he also be
able to, should that also infer, should we infer from that that
actually a non-כהן Kohen. can do it? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like
this,
okay.
They kind of undermined the original premise and they created a new
category, right? Because the whole assumption was that if you're not an
עבודה avoda you definitely don't need a כהן. Kohen. And now we're
saying no, there's a category of things that are really not עבודה
avodah, and have nothing to do with בית המקדש and they might
need a כהן. Kohen Basically the non-כהן Kohen category.
Right. But within the world of קרבנות, korbanos, you're right, meaning outside
the world of קרבנות korbanos it's not relevant. Within the world of
קרבנות korbanos there seems to be a relationship between if a non-כהן
Kohen can do it it's not עבודה, avodah if a כהן Kohen
can do it it is an עבודה. avodah, And therefore we want
to say for רבי שמעון that since he downgrades הולכה—now holacha I
would not have said he calls it a non-עבודה, avodah but the
גמרא Gemara threw in that phrase—he downgrades הולכה, holacha that means he
considers הולכה holacha. non-עבודה, avodah that should lead to the assumption that
a non-כהן Kohen can do it. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this,
okay. והרי הולכת איברים לכבש, ve-harei holachas eivarim lakevesh, how about the
bringing of the limbs of the sacrifice to the ramp? דעבודה שאפשר
לבטלה היא, da-avoda she-efshar levatelah hi, you can do that with, you
could שחט shacht an animal right at the edge of the ramp,
okay, so you don't actually have to bring them to the ramp.
Okay. ופסולה בזר, u-pesula bezar, and we know that only a כהן
Kohen can do the transporting of this. So if only a כהן
Kohen can transport the limbs, presumably only a כהן Kohen can transport
the blood. Now how do you know רבי שמעון would admit to
that? That only a כהן Kohen can transport the limbs? דכתיב, והקריב
הכהן את הכל והקטיר המזבחה. vehikriv hakohen es hakol vehiktir hamizbeachah. It's
pretty clear the כהן Kohen should bring it all close and burn
it on the altar. ואמר מר זו הולכת איברים לכבש. ve-amar mar
zu holachas eivarim lakevesh. That's bringing the limbs to the ramp. So
the גמרא Gemara says, היכא דגלי גלי, היכא דלא גלי לא גלי.
heicha degali gali, heicha delo gali lo gali. Where the תורה says
explicitly it says explicitly. Okay, it's sort of like the פרה אדומה
para aduma answer. That's גזירת הכתוב. gezeiras hakasuv. Okay. But since we
don't have an explicit verse by the bringing of the blood, it
would be quite ironic that a non-כהן Kohen can bring the blood
but only a כהן Kohen can bring the limbs. But that's the
גמרא Gemara still wants to say, maybe according to רבי שמעון who
downgrades הולכה, holacha. maybe a non-כהן Kohen could bring the blood even
though you need a כהן Kohen. to bring the limbs. But of
course the גמרא Gemara is not satisfied. ולאו כל דכן הוא? ve-lav
kol dachen hu? One minute, isn't it a קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
ומה הולכת איברים לכבש דלא מעכבא כפרה, u-mah holachas eivarim lakevesh d-lo
me'akva kapara, the bringing the limbs to the ramp that is not
central for the sacrifice to achieve
atonement, right? It
doesn't, it doesn't, it doesn't determine the effectiveness of the sacrifice, it's
not a necessary part of the sacrifice being valid. בעי כהונה, ba'ei
kehuna, and that needs a כהן. Kohen הולכת דם דמעכבא כפרה, holachas
dam d-me'akva kapara, the bringing of the blood which prevents it from
being, you know, which is central to it being valid, okay, at
least during the process of the blood. Maybe in theory you could
do away with the הולכה, holacha. but right now the sacrifice isn't
valid until you get the blood to the altar and sprinkle the
blood on the altar. לא כל שכן? lo kol sheken? Isn't it
certainly true? Doesn't it certainly stand to reason? So the גמרא Gemara
basically is sort of, you know, saying, look give me a break.
Even for רבי שמעון, this is an עבודה, avodah and even if
in theory you could do without it, once we sort of see
the evidence from the bringing of the limbs to the ramp, this
needs a כהן Kohen as
well. איתמר נמי, אמר עולא אמר רבי אלעזר, הולכה בזר פסולה אפילו
רבי שמעון. itmar nami, amar Ulla amar Rabbi Elazar, holacha bezar pesula
afilu Rabbi Shimon. Carrying the blood, a non-כהן Kohen, carrying it invalidates
even for רבי שמעון. So the way I would say it is
the גמרא Gemara was toying with the idea that for רבי שמעון
it's not, does not constitute an עבודה. But when it finally concludes
that you need a כהן, Kohen it's concluding assuming that strong identity
that the גמרא gemara suggested. It concludes that it is an עבודה
even for רבי שמעון. Because in theory you could do away with
it, maybe your מחשבה machshava doesn't invalidate, but it is an עבודה
and if done by a non-כהן kohen it's invalid. Okay. Now איבעיא
להו. ibaia lehu. Now we get back to the question we raised
before. הולכה
שלא ברגל שמה הולכה או לא שמה הולכה. holacha she-lo beragel shemah
holacha o lo shemah holacha. What is the story... if you just
did like, you know, nobody has to walk to get the blood
to the altar? You know, one כהן kohen hands it to the
next, hands it to the next, hands it to the next, whatever,
and you could do a total הולכה holacha, without moving your foot.
The reverse of ל"ט
מלאכות.
lamed
tes melochos.
Alright, what do you mean?
To do
כעין
השבת במקדש ke'ein hashabbos bamikdash and then there would be הוצאה. hotza'ah.
Right, exactly. So the question is does it constitute הולכה? holacha, Now
this is a two-pronged question. One part of the question is like
do I have to redo it, right? So let's say that if
you passed it from there to the altar without transporting it and
that's not considered an act of הולכה, holacha. I have to get
the blood back and then I have to walk it back. Now
that's interesting because you could have said who says you need an
act of הולכה? holacha If I can make this blood magically disappear
here and reappear by the altar, because the rabbis would admit that
if you שחט shechted it right by the altar you don't need
הולכה. holacha But here there's an assumption that if it wasn't שחט
shechted right by the altar and there's a distance to traverse, the
assumption is that halachically you must do an act of הולכה holacha
to traverse that distance. Okay? I mean, let's say you exactly like
threw it, you know, and somebody caught it, you need to do
an act of הולכה holacha to traverse that distance. So therefore if
you need... the question is does it need to be by foot
or not? Okay, the other question is do you invalidate? If I
did this, okay, and you say no, no, no, go do it
again, that doesn't count. Okay, it didn't count. But what that also
means is while I'm doing this, let's say I'm thinking שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo or I'm thinking חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. So if what
I'm doing is not an עבודה, my מחשבה machshava doesn't invalidate. So
it would mean there'd be a plus and a minus. If it's
not an עבודה we've got to bring it back and do it
again, but it also means that my מחשבה doesn't invalidate. If it
is an עבודה, that means it was good, but it means that
my מחשבה does invalidate. Okay, also you could ask what's the story
if a non-כהן kohen does it? Okay? If it's not an עבודה
then it's nothing, bring it back and do it again. If it's
an עבודה then a non-כהן kohen did an עבודה and he invalidated
the blood.
Yes? I read a description, but I don't know if this is
that at פסח Pesach the כהנים kohanim lined up and they handed
it from one to the other.
Yeah, so we're going to get exactly to that. Okay. Excellent. So
let's take a look. תא שמע: ta shema: וכן יושב וכן שמאל.
vechen yoshev vechen smol. Sitting or your left hand invalidates by the
receipt of the blood, by the transporting of the blood. פסול. posul.
Now so how do you sit and transport the blood? How do
you sit and transport the blood? Presumably you sit and transport the
blood, you sit and you hand it. You do exactly that. And
it says it's invalid because you're sitting. So that suggests that if
you're standing and doing the same thing, it's כשר. kosher. Okay? העומד
דומיא דיושב, ha'omed dumya deyoshev, standing like that is כשר. kosher. So
you see that that is considered a valid הולכה. So the גמרא
says no, דילמא יושב דקשיף מישף. dilma yoshev de'kashif meishaf. Okay, no,
you can sit and transport it by scooting along. You don't have
to stand to move.
Could you sit in the עזרה? azarah?
That's a different question. No, you're not allowed to sit, but that's
a different question. Okay, anyway. Okay, but you can
sit and scoot along. And
therefore העומד דומיא דיושב דנייד פורתא, ha'omed dumya deyoshev denayad purta, standing
would mean you're moving a little, like whatever. And that is כשר.
kosher. So you can't infer from the invalidity of sitting that handing
while you're standing is okay. Okay, we still could be talking about
with a movement of the body. תא שמע מן הכא, ta shema
min hacha, come and hear, okay: שחט ישראל, shachat Yisrael, David's point,
by the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, the ישראל Yisrael would שחט, shecht,
וקיבל הכהן, vekibel hakohen, the כהן kohen would catch it, נתן לחבירו
וחבירו לחבירו, nasan lechavero vechavero lechavero, you know, one to the next,
a whole Chinese fire brigade, and therefore it would be good. So
nobody... there it's also just handing. So the גמרא says התם נמי
דנייד פורתא. hatam nami denayad purta. No, maybe what it means is
I get it and I take a step and hand it, and
then the next one takes a step and... now that's interesting because
even if I'm taking a step, is my step traversing the whole
distance? You know, so it's not so clear, right? But anyway, like
if you're... if the other guy is next to me, right? Presumably
even if I'm moving a little and getting right next to him,
my arm is presumably moving to get it half his body, you
know, across the width of his body to get it into his
hands. So it's a little funny that the גמרא seems like if
you incorporate an act of movement into what you're doing, that's an
act of הולכה. We don't ask by every millimeter did this thing
move through an act of movement of the body, you know, through
an act of moving of your body. What we ask is did
the act of transporting it
involve incorporating moving your body, and if you were moving your body
as you were transporting it, even if there was a certain amount
that was done by your arms, that's considered הולכה. That seems to
be the case. Let's just finish this. Okay. ומאי קמשמע לן: umai
kamashma lan: ברוב עם הדרת מלך. berov am hadrat melech. So the
חידוש chidush there is not to tell you something about הולכה, but
to tell you we wanted to get as many כהנים kohanim involved,
it's makes it very nice. תא שמע, ta shema, the last proof:
קיבל הכשר ונתן. kibel hakosher venasan. So it's on the פסול, pasul,
יחזיר לכשר. yachzir lakasher. So a כשר kosher כהן kohen catches it,
hands it to me, I'm a פסול pasul כהן kohen, or a
non-כהן, kohen so the הלכה halacha is, what do I do? I
have to hand it back to the כהן kohen and do it
again. Okay,
so the fact that יחזיר לכשר. yachzir lakasher. So the fact that
I have to hand it back to the כהן kohen shows that
his act of handing it to me was not a הולכה, right?
Because I didn't invalidate it yet, I'm like doing a משא אסטבא.
massa istaba. He's just putting it on my hands. You get the
idea? So the כהן kohen put it on my hands. So I
haven't invalidated it. So why doesn't another כהן kohen come and pick
it from my hands and take it further? Why do we have
to reverse it? It must be the act of him stretching his
arm and putting it on my hands was, does not constitute a
הולכה. That seems to be what the problem is. So the גמרא
says no, אימא יחזור הכשר ויקבלה. eima yachzor hakasher veykablah. No, no,
what you don't have to read it that I hand it back,
the כהן kohen takes it back from me. You can read it
another כהן kohen can come and take it from me and continue
to move it forward. Alright? So did the initial כהן kohen stretching
his arm and putting it on my hands was that an act
of הולכה that has to be now reversed? Was it an act
of הולכה that doesn't have to be reversed that the next כהן
kohen can take it from me and move it forward? Or was
it not an act of הולכה that has to be reversed and
has to be given back to the כהן to do over? Two
ways of reading that ברייתא. braitah. So in the end of the
day we do not conclude whether
הולכה requires actual traversing with your body, הולכה ברגל, holacha beregel, does
it require stepping and moving or is it enough to just do
it like by passing and so on? That remains an open question.